Register of the Andrei Mikhailovich Naidenov Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Andrei Mikhailovich Naidenov papers
1944-1972
2000C78
Hoover Institution Archives
3 microfilm reels (0.45 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, and personal documents, relating to anti-communist movements in the United States.
Naidenov, Andrei Mikhailovich, 1896-
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
A. M. Naidenov was born in Moscow on 30 June 1896. After graduation from the Moscow Commercial Institute in 1917, he worked in the Soviet Union as an economist in various organizations, including "Azneft'" and the People's
Commissariat of Light Industry of the Azerbaidzhan S.S.R., where he was a planner for ten years. This experience led him to author a study entitled Administration of Azerbaijani Industry, published by the Research Studies Institute of the Air University in 1952.
Escaping the USSR during the Second World War (1944), he moved to the United States in 1949, working as a draftsman in New York in addition to engaging in anti-Communist activities as a journalist and an announcer for the Voice of America. Most of his writings and correspondence are concerned with problems of anti-communism. Naidenov died in San Francisco in September 1972.
Chronology
1896 June 30 Born, Moscow, Russia
1917 Graduated, Moskovskii kommercheskii institut
1917-1944 Worked as an economist for various Soviet governmental organizations, including 10 years as a planner in the Ministry of Industry of the Azerbaidzhan S.S.R.
1948 November 19 Entered the United States
1952 Author, Administration of Azerbaijani Industry
? (after 1972) Died
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains materials relating mainly to the anti-Communist activities of A. M. Naidenov, an émigré from the Soviet Union. The biographical file reflects his campaign to acquire U. S. citizenship. The correspondence and his main written work, "What Is the Communist Threat?," reflect his views on the international political situation and the struggle against Communism.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco, as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Anti-communist movements--United States.; Communism.; Russia (Federation); Russians--United States.; Soviet Union.; United States--Politics and government.
- Biographical File, 1944-1958 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Autobiographical note, identity papers, letters of introduction, scrapbook, papers relating to application for citizenship and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1947-1968 (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1948-1972 (Box 1-2)
  Articles, reviews, book, arranged chronologically by title
- Subject File, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
  Appeals, clippings, correspondence, lectures, reports and writings, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 3)
  One photograph of A. M. Naidenov
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1944-1958 (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical note (Folder 1: 1)
  - Identity papers (Folder 1: 2)
  - Letters of introduction (Folder 1: 3)
  - Scrapbook of clippings about Naidenov (Folder 1: 4)
  - Subject file
    - Citizenship. (Folder 1: 5)
      Includes letters of recommendation for Naidenov from various people, correspondence with officials, statements, and similar matter
    - Driver's license examination (Folder 1: 6)
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 7)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1947-1968
  - General, 1960-1964 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Allilueva, Svetlana, 1968 (Folder 1: 9)
    General note
    See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/"What Is the Communist Threat?"
  - Goldwater, Barry, 1964-1965
    See SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/"What Is the Communist Threat?"
  - Kennan, George F., 1956-1967 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1947 (Folder 1: 11)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1948-1972
  For brief lectures on various famous Russian writers prepared for Kruzhok literaturnye vstrechi, see SUBJECT FILE
  - General
    - General, 1963-1972 and undated (Folder 1: 12)
      Notes, letters to the editor, reviews of plays, lectures, and events, and other minor, mostly untitled, pieces
    - Poetry, n.d. (Folder 1: 13)
      Holograph and typescript
    - Scrapbook, 1948-1965 (Folder 1: 14)
      Consists of clippings of articles and letters to the editor
  - "Dobrovol'tsy,", n.d. (Folder 1: 15)
    Typescript
  - "Filosofiia sluchaia,", n.d. (Folder 1: 16)
    Holograph
  - "Na doklade Georgiia Adamovicha,", n.d. (Folder 1: 17)
  - "Petr Velikii, kak preobrazovatel' Rossii," speech, n.d. (Folder 1: 18)
  - "Vospominaniia moskvicha,", n.d. (Folder 1: 19)
    Holograph and typescript. Includes correspondence
  - Administration of Azerbaijani Industry, 1952 (Folder 1: 20)
    Printed copy and correspondence, 1953
  - "The Assassination of the President,"., 1967 (Folder 1: 21)
    Holograph and typescript. Includes correspondence and earlier drafts from 1963
  - "What Is the Communist Threat?,", 1967
    - General
      - Correspondence, 1952-1967 (Folder 1: 22)
        For additional correspondence with Allilueva, see CORRESPONDENCE.
        Includes correspondence with Senators Barry Goldwater and Everett Dirksen, and Svetlana Allilueva
      - Diagrams and illustrative material (Folder 1: 23)
      - Notes, background materials, tentative tables of contents (Folder 1: 24)
    - Russian drafts
      - Holograph (Folder 2: 1)
      - Typescript. (Folder 2: 2-3)
        Includes handwritten notes
    - English draft
      - Typescript (Folder 2: 4-5)
      - Typescript (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
  - "Baku,"., 1970 (Folder 3: 3)
  - "Pamiati Chaikovskogo,"., 1970 August 23 (Folder 3: 4)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - Review of S. I. Popov, Moi vospominaniia, Rossiia, 1972 May 12 (Folder 3: 5)
    Printed copy
- SUBJECT FILE, 1970-1972
  Appeals, clippings, correspondence, lectures, reports and writings
  - Kruzhok literaturnye vstrechi, San Francisco. (Folder 3: 6)
    Includes correspondence regarding its activities, notes and brief lectures on various famous Russian writers
  - Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco. (Folder 3: 7)
    Includes appeals, correspondence, reports and other matter
  - Russian Center, San Francisco (Folder 3: 8)
- PHOTOGRAPH, n.d. (Folder 3: 9)